<story-context id=".bmad/bmm/workflows/4-implementation/story-context/template" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>3</epicId>
    <storyId>3.6</storyId>
    <title>Enhance README as Living Document</title>
    <status>drafted</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-11-19</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/sprint-artifacts/3-6-enhance-readme-as-living-document.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>

  <story>
    <asA>developer</asA>
    <iWant>the `/infra/README.md` updated with deployment details and maintenance process</iWant>
    <soThat>documentation evolves with the infrastructure and remains accurate</soThat>
    <tasks>
      - Task 1: Analyze current README structure and identify gaps (AC: #1)
      - Task 2: Add Deployment Process section (AC: #1, #3)
      - Task 3: Enhance Testing section (AC: #1)
      - Task 4: Add Infrastructure Changes section (AC: #1, #3)
      - Task 5: Add Maintenance section (AC: #1, #2)
      - Task 6: Update document header (AC: #2)
      - Task 7: Verify all command examples use correct AWS profile (AC: #3)
      - Task 8: Validate README completeness (AC: #1, #2, #3, #4)
      - Task 9: Commit README changes (AC: #4)
    </tasks>
  </story>

  <acceptanceCriteria>
    1. README includes new sections:
       - Section 6: Deployment Process (build, deploy, verify, access pattern)
       - Section 7: Testing (unit tests, integration test, linting)
       - Section 8: Infrastructure Changes (when to redeploy infrastructure vs files)
       - Section 9: Maintenance (document version, review cadence, update responsibility)

    2. Document header includes:
       - Last Updated: 2025-11-18
       - Document Version: 1.1
       - Review: Update this README when infrastructure changes

    3. All command examples use correct AWS profile (NDX/InnovationSandboxHub)

    4. README updated in git with commit: `docs(infra): enhance README with deployment and maintenance`
  </acceptanceCriteria>

  <artifacts>
    <docs>
      <item>
        <path>docs/epics.md</path>
        <title>Epic Breakdown</title>
        <section>Story 3.6: Enhance README as Living Document</section>
        <snippet>Documentation as living document, not one-time artifact. Include version/date to track when last updated. Maintenance section establishes update responsibility. Monthly review cadence or when infrastructure changes.</snippet>
      </item>
      <item>
        <path>docs/sprint-artifacts/tech-spec-epic-3.md</path>
        <title>Epic 3 Technical Specification</title>
        <section>AC6: Living Documentation, NFR-MAINT-5</section>
        <snippet>README includes version and last updated date. Maintenance section establishes update responsibility. Monthly review cadence or when infrastructure changes. Developer making changes updates documentation.</snippet>
      </item>
      <item>
        <path>docs/infrastructure-architecture.md</path>
        <title>NDX Infrastructure Architecture</title>
        <section>Data Architecture, Access Pattern Decision</section>
        <snippet>CloudFront required for site access. Site not publicly accessible in MVP. Files uploaded successfully but return 403 Forbidden. Bucket has BLOCK_ALL public access per security requirements.</snippet>
      </item>
      <item>
        <path>docs/sprint-artifacts/3-5-create-integration-test-for-aws-deployment.md</path>
        <title>Story 3.5: Create Integration Test for AWS Deployment</title>
        <section>Dev Agent Record, Completion Notes</section>
        <snippet>Integration test documentation added to README (lines 101-130). Documentation pattern established: clear structure with "What it does", "Issues caught", "When to run" subsections. AWS profile consistency maintained throughout.</snippet>
      </item>
      <item>
        <path>docs/epics.md</path>
        <title>Epic Breakdown</title>
        <section>Story 3.1 & 3.2: Deployment Automation</section>
        <snippet>Root package.json has yarn deploy script pointing to scripts/deploy.sh. Deploy script validates _site/ exists, uses AWS CLI S3 sync with profile, includes file count validation, sets cache control headers, error recovery via idempotent re-runs.</snippet>
      </item>
    </docs>
    <code>
      <item>
        <path>infra/README.md</path>
        <kind>documentation</kind>
        <symbol>N/A</symbol>
        <lines>1-325</lines>
        <reason>Current README file to be enhanced. Contains version 1.0, last updated 2025-11-18. Existing sections: Overview, Prerequisites, Initial Setup, Development Workflow, Site Access, Troubleshooting, Project Structure, Additional Resources. Integration test documentation added in Story 3.5 (lines 101-130).</reason>
      </item>
      <item>
        <path>scripts/deploy.sh</path>
        <kind>bash script</kind>
        <symbol>deploy.sh</symbol>
        <lines>1-29</lines>
        <reason>Deployment script referenced in new Deployment Process section. Uses AWS CLI S3 sync with --profile NDX/InnovationSandboxHub, validates _site/ exists, includes file count validation, outputs success message.</reason>
      </item>
      <item>
        <path>package.json</path>
        <kind>config</kind>
        <symbol>scripts.deploy</symbol>
        <lines>11</lines>
        <reason>Root package.json deploy script (line 11: "deploy": "scripts/deploy.sh"). Referenced in Deployment Process section as the command to run from project root.</reason>
      </item>
      <item>
        <path>infra/package.json</path>
        <kind>config</kind>
        <symbol>scripts</symbol>
        <lines>1-30</lines>
        <reason>Infrastructure package.json with lint and test scripts referenced in Testing section. Contains: "lint": "eslint .", "test": "jest".</reason>
      </item>
    </code>
    <dependencies>
      <node>
        <name>@11ty/eleventy</name>
        <version>^3.1.2</version>
        <scope>devDependencies</scope>
        <reason>Static site generator - builds _site/ directory that gets deployed</reason>
      </node>
      <aws>
        <tool>AWS CLI v2.x</tool>
        <profile>NDX/InnovationSandboxHub</profile>
        <region>us-west-2</region>
        <reason>Required for S3 sync operations in deployment script. All commands must use --profile flag.</reason>
      </aws>
      <cdk>
        <tool>AWS CDK</tool>
        <version>2.x</version>
        <reason>Infrastructure deployment tool. Commands must use --profile flag for infrastructure changes.</reason>
      </cdk>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>

  <constraints>
    - All AWS CLI commands MUST include `--profile NDX/InnovationSandboxHub` flag
    - All CDK commands MUST include `--profile NDX/InnovationSandboxHub` flag
    - Document version must be incremented from 1.0 to 1.1
    - Last updated date must be set to 2025-11-18 (or current date)
    - Follow existing README structure and markdown formatting patterns
    - Preserve existing content quality and documentation style from Story 3.5
    - Maintain consistency with subsection patterns: purpose, commands, expected output
    - Document must explain CloudFront is required for site access (per Story 2.3 decision)
    - Git commit message must be: `docs(infra): enhance README with deployment and maintenance`
    - Only modify infra/README.md file (no other files)
    - README sections must be logically ordered and numbered
  </constraints>

  <interfaces>
    <item>
      <name>yarn deploy</name>
      <kind>CLI command</kind>
      <signature>yarn deploy (from project root)</signature>
      <path>package.json line 11</path>
    </item>
    <item>
      <name>scripts/deploy.sh</name>
      <kind>Bash script</kind>
      <signature>bash scripts/deploy.sh</signature>
      <path>scripts/deploy.sh</path>
    </item>
    <item>
      <name>AWS CLI S3 sync</name>
      <kind>CLI command</kind>
      <signature>aws s3 sync _site/ s3://ndx-static-prod/ --profile NDX/InnovationSandboxHub --delete --exact-timestamps --cache-control "public, max-age=3600" --exclude ".DS_Store"</signature>
      <path>scripts/deploy.sh lines 12-17</path>
    </item>
    <item>
      <name>CDK deploy</name>
      <kind>CLI command</kind>
      <signature>cdk deploy --profile NDX/InnovationSandboxHub</signature>
      <path>Referenced in Infrastructure Changes section</path>
    </item>
    <item>
      <name>yarn build</name>
      <kind>CLI command</kind>
      <signature>yarn build (from project root)</signature>
      <path>package.json line 10</path>
    </item>
  </interfaces>

  <tests>
    <standards>
      README validation standards:
      - All sections present and complete (Overview, Prerequisites, Initial Setup, Development Workflow, Testing, Deployment Process, Infrastructure Changes, Site Access, Troubleshooting, Project Structure, Maintenance, Additional Resources)
      - All command examples use correct AWS profile (NDX/InnovationSandboxHub)
      - Markdown formatting valid (no broken links, proper code blocks, heading hierarchy)
      - Links to other documents working (../docs/*.md paths)
      - Commands are copy-paste ready (include full flags and parameters)
      - No typos or clarity issues
      - Version header updated (1.0 → 1.1)
      - Last updated date current (2025-11-18)
    </standards>

    <locations>
      infra/README.md - Target file to be enhanced
    </locations>

    <ideas>
      AC1 Testing Ideas:
      - Verify all 4 new sections added (Deployment Process, Testing, Infrastructure Changes, Maintenance)
      - Verify Deployment Process section includes: build command, deploy command, smoke test placeholder, access pattern explanation
      - Verify Testing section reorganized from Development Workflow with unit tests, integration tests, linting
      - Verify Infrastructure Changes section explains when to use cdk deploy vs yarn deploy
      - Verify Maintenance section includes version 1.1, last updated date, review cadence, update responsibility, version history table

      AC2 Testing Ideas:
      - Verify document header updated with Last Updated: 2025-11-18
      - Verify document header updated with Document Version: 1.1
      - Verify document header includes Review instruction

      AC3 Testing Ideas:
      - Scan README for all bash command examples
      - Verify all aws commands include --profile NDX/InnovationSandboxHub
      - Verify all cdk commands include --profile NDX/InnovationSandboxHub
      - Check existing sections and new sections for profile consistency

      AC4 Testing Ideas:
      - Verify git commit created with exact message: "docs(infra): enhance README with deployment and maintenance"
      - Verify only infra/README.md included in commit (no unintended files)
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>
